Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the American Postal Workers Union PE.026
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the American Postal Workers Union
1969-2003
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.026
1.6 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 1 flat file folder, and 1 shared manuscript box
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the American Postal Workers Union (APWU) (1969-2003) is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. The collection consists of agreements, contracts, constitutions, and convention proceedings, as well as printed ephemera, such as fliers, circular letters, newspaper clippings, pamphlets and other publications. In general, material in the collection comes from the national body of the union, however there is material from the New York Metro Postal Union, as well as from various rank and file committees.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Postal Workers Union: Moe Biller Files (WAG 99)
New York Area Postal Union Records (WAG 103)
Historical Note
The American Postal Workers Union (APWU) was founded out of the "Great Postal Strike of 1970", in which thousands of postal employees struck in New York City and across the country successfully winning an increase in wages and collective bargaining power through the Postal Reorganization Act. The Union was formed as a merger of five postal unions. Following founding, the APWU jointly bargained with several other postal unions around the country an agreement with the United States Postal Service. In 1994, the APWU began bargaining with the USPS on its own, and has an agreement approved by members running through 2010.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the American Postal Workers Union (APWU) (1969-2003) consists of contracts, agreements, constitutions, and convention proceedings, as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, circular letters, newspaper clippings, pamphlets and publications. The collection contains printed material on employee benefits, national union elections, occupational safety and health, women in the workplace and sexual harassment. There are several publications from the Research and Education Department, including steward's and organizing manuals. There is a series of circular letters entitled, "Communicating Directly with You, the Members," which conveys updates and organizing efforts by the national leaders to the union members. The collection contains newspapers clippings and publications about the APWU and some of its important contracts, providing a source of general introductory information, included as well are two more substantial sources for history on the union. There are materials from several rank and file groups, including the Postal Workers Defense Committee, the Outlaw Caucus, and the Workers for One Postal Union.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. There is no accession record associated with this collection.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
Postal service -- Employees -- Labor unions; Clippings (information artifacts); Press releases.; Fliers (printed matter); Printed ephemera.; Posters.; Circular letters.; Agreements.; Constitutions.; Contracts; Labor unions -- United States.; Labor unions; Postal service -- Employees.; Labor unions -- New York (N.Y.); American Postal Workers Union; New York Metro Area Postal Union
- Agreements and Contracts, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
- Agreements and Contracts, 1981 (Box 1)
- Agreements and Contracts, 1982-1985 (Box 1)
- Agreements and Contracts, 1987 (Box 1)
- Agreements and Contracts, 1990 (Box 1)
- Agreements and Contracts, 1994 (Box 1)
- Agreements and Contracts, 1998-2000 (Box 1)
- Benefits, 1978-1984, undated (Box 1)
- Circular Letters, 1980-1984 (Box 1)
- Circular Letters, 1984-2001 (Box 1)
- Constitutional Conventions, 1980 (Box 1)
- Constitutions, 1978-1998 (Box 1)
- Department of Human Resources, 1980-1981, undated (Box 1)
- Elections, 1978-1982, circa 1986 (Box 1)
- The Federal Page, 1983-2000 (Box 1)
- Fliers and Ephemera, 1979-1998, undated (Box 1)
- History, undated (Box 1)
- Memoranda of Understanding, 1978-1981, undated (Box 1)
- New York Metro Area Postal Union, 1974-1986, undated (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 191, Folder 13)
- News Service, 1973-1990 (Box 1)
- Newspaper Clippings on and Publications Relating to, 1973-1975, 1995-2003 (Box 1)
- Occupational Safety and Health, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
- Outlaw Caucus, 1971-1974, undated (Box 1)
- Pamphlets and Publications, 1976-1979, 1990, undated (Box 1)
- Post Office Department (Washington, DC), 1969 (Box 1)
- Postal Workers Defense Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
- Posters, 1989-1991, undated (Box 1)
- Posters (Oversize), 1995 (Flat-file-folder 6)
- Press Releases, 1980, undated (Box 1)
- Research and Education Department, 1974-1980 (Box 1)
- Testimonies, 1980 (Box 1)
- Workers for One Postal Union, 1991 (Box 1)